[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
okay periodic a periodic uh uh line can
either mean particle really moving on a
circle or it could just be a rule that
you have a finite length of line and
your rule is whenever the particle gets
to this point over here it instantly
reappears at the other end of the line
just a rule that
uh you could wrap it in a circle if you
wanted to in your mind's eye but that
doesn't necessarily mean that the object
is moving in a circle it's moving on
what is called a periodic line so that
motion is periodic if you disappear out
this end you reappear on this end under
these circumstances the the analog or
the analog statement for quantum
mechanics is that the wave function s of
X should be
periodic s of X let's call this distance
l s of X should equal s of x +
L that's the notion of a periodic wave
function the infinite line with a line
grows to Infinity is the limit of a
periodic line where the length goes to
Infinity so you can study quantum
mechanics or waves any kind of field
Theory as the limit of a field Theory or
a Schrodinger equation or what whatever
it happens to be even just particle
mechanics on a periodic line and the
limit that the line gets infinite for
ordinary particle classical particle
mechanics there's not much advantage in
thinking about it periodically but in
quantum mechanics it is very very useful
to to begin with a periodic line now
since s of X has to be equal to S of X
Plus L that has as was pointed out a
moment ago that has implications for the
spectrum of momentum for the possible
igen values of momentum remember the
wave functions for a momentum igen state
are e to the I
PX incidentally this is not quite the
ortho P being oh this is not right is it
I'm missing
something H bar H bar in the
denominator and we often call that e to
the I
KX K is just momentum divided by H bar I
think I'll use the K
notation or you can simply work in units
where Plank's constant is equal to one
and then K and P are the same
thing okay that's the this is the wave
function but it's not properly
normalized remember the rule for a
normalized wave function
is that the integral of s star s should
be equal to one that's basically the
statement that the total probability of
finding the object someplace should add
up to one if I take this wave
function with p as a parameter and I
multiply by it by its
conjugate s star s would just be equal
to one and if I then did this integral
then oh I'm sorry you know what I want
to I want to go back one step I want to
think of L as equal to 2 pi
r i want to imagine that it is on a
circle this is just for notational uh
convenience to think of it as on a
circle
um and then this would not be true s
star s is one but then the integral over
x from 0 to 2 pi r would not be one it
would just be 2 pi r
so what I would do to fix it is I would
divide the wave function here by the
square root of 2 pi
r then when I did the integral the
integral of s star s for each of these
momentum IG IG functions they would be
normalized so that the total probability
would be equal to one everybody
understand why I put square root there I
put square root there because when we
multiply s star s the square root from
here will combine well the square root
from here will be uh squared and the
integral will be one instead of
uh instead of what I have there okay
that's this is I only mention this
because you're going to see two pies all
over the place this is where they come
from they're not very
interesting uh but that is where they
come from now or you could say that the
defition of
L no okay however you well the
definition of length doesn't have a
square root the definition of the wave
function has a square root no I mean the
reason you chose the square root there
is
you're trying to get unit length unit
length for the vectors yeah for these
vectors yeah yeah yeah yeah not for this
length right that's right that's right
um once we have that we look at the
individual wave functions these wave
functions for given momentum and we
require that they're periodic that says
that
K time 2i
R that's the value of the exponent here
when you've gone one full cycle around
that must equal 2 N Pi 2 N pi
in other
words the W if the wave function over
here let's say the wave function over
here is one then over here it will
contain the factor e to the i k and then
X will equal 2i
R if the wave function is to be periodic
then e to the i k * 2 pi r must equal
one and the only way that that can
happen is if 2 pi r k is equal to an
integer multiple of 2 pi all right so
that would just say that uh that the
length R * K must
equal an
integer or that the igen value K this is
the igen value of the momentum or
strictly speaking it's the igen value of
the momentum times a divided by H
bar the quantity k is quantized in units
of n / r
all right now this
means that if I were the plot on the
horizontal axis here the spectrum of
possible values of K I'm not making a
graph I'm just going to put down all the
possible points K that uh they form a
discrete
collection with a spacing which is 1 /
R
so there they
are those are the possible values of K
starting at zero going off to negative
Infinity going off to positive
infinity and the separation between
them is 1/
k Sorry one/
R so as R gets bigger and bigger the
spacing between different values of K
neighboring values of K get smaller and
smaller and eventually we can say that
when the r AIS gets infinitely big the
uh spacing between neighboring values of
K shrinks to zero and I can say just
about every value of K is
possible or there's no there's no value
of K which isn't arbitrarily close to
one allowable they get dense they get
dense we might as well just say every
value of K becomes possible
that's in that limit now next step to go
to the limit in which the igen values
become very very dense or before we do
that before we do that let's just notice
that without proving it since we've
already proved it since these wave
functions are igen vectors of a Herm
Mission operator for different values of
K they must be
orthogonal okay this is true if we
calculate the integral from 0 to 2 pi r
of e to the i k
x * e to minus I let's call it K Prime X
where K and K Prime are allowable
values then this integral is one sorry
we have to put a 1 over 2 pi in 1 over 2
pi r in that's this normalization Factor
here 1 over 2 pi r on the outside
we do this
integral it will be 1 if K is equal to K
Prime that's obvious if K is equal to K
Prime then this isn't here this product
is one and it's just the integral from 0
to 2 pi r / 2 pi r that's one if K is
not equal to K Prime then the integral
is zero okay the integral is zero
because basically what you're doing
these things are made out of signs and
cosiness
right this one is made out of functions
which oscillate like this this one is
made out of functions which oscillate
with a different
period and the product will be
positive some places and negative other
places here the product is negative here
the product is positive if we take two
different values of K and look at it
along the line we find that it cancels
as much as it adds the result of that is
that this integral is always zero for K
not equal to K Prime so there's an easy
way to say it this is just equal to a
chronica Delta a thing which is zero if
K is not equal to K Prime and 1 if K is
equal to K Prime now K itself is not
quite an integer K is related to an
integer and so we' actually write is
that this is equal to Delta of n and n
Prime where n and n Prime are the
appropriate integers going with K and K
Prime that's that's
standard quantum mechanics raising its
head for us
orthonormal igen functions being the
igen functions of a heran operator so
that's good all of that is
good yes is that a definition no this is
not a definition this is a theorem theem
oh
yeah yeah the value of integrals is
never
well uh the value of integrals is a
general rule for well-defined functions
is something you
calculate okay but what I'm not clear
with is is where does that come from
where do you are you just trying to show
that the two-way functions of you're
asking me can I prove this no no no I'm
asking where does it come from because
they are igen vectors with different
igen values of a Herm Mission operator
it implies that they're orthogonal okay
and that that shows yeah yeah this is a
either we can think of this as a
consequence of the fact that they're
igen functions of a Herm Mission
operator or we can say this is
confirmation of the uh of that uh fact
yeah there signs and coin that are
periodic over the same interval they're
periodic over the same interval but they
don't have the same wav they're going to
inte if they do have the same wave
if they that's right that's all yeah
that's all that's happening right right
for
example uh well yes that's right if they
don't have the same wavelength uh uh
they will cancel out as much as they
add okay so this is an example of the
orthonormality the
orthonormal character of the igen
functions of a Herm Mission
operator in other words these operator
these these uh functions thought of as
vectors form a basis for the vector
space uh the next step if we were trying
to get to this Continuum limit we want
to
replace sums by integrals and chronic
Deltas by Delta functions I'm not going
to go into that very much except to tell
you that to do so what we basically do
is we multiply up these each of these
wave functions by a large number in
other words instead of taking wave
functions which are in the standard
sense normalized to one we multiply we
multiply them by a big number how big a
number we simply multiply them by the
square root of
R if we take each wave function of this
type and multiply it by the squ root of
R it's no longer a truly normalized wave
function but now we'll just Define it s
p of X will instead of being this thing
it'll be the same thing e to the I
PX over the square < TK of Pi sare < TK
of 2
pi 2
pi uh without the r here that means
these wave functions have been sced
stretched out by a factor of
R right this sorry stretched out by a
factor of square root of R now that's
not going to change the fact that if we
take two different ones where did I put
it if we take two different ones that
the integral will be zero that's not
going to be affected by multiplying by R
it'll be
zero if K is not equal to K Prime that
will still be true but what if K is
equal to K Prime originally we had zero
there I'm sorry originally we had one
there if K is equal to K Prime we had
one now we're going to get something big
if we get rid of
the
uh if we get if we stretch out the
vectors by a factor of square root of R
then on the right hand side
we will get
R if K is equal to K
Prime in other words we now have that
the inner product between these two
functions as a function of notice it is
a function of K minus K Prime if I
combine these exponentials together it
really just becomes K minus K
Prime
X it's a function of K minus K Prime it
has the property it's zero if K is not
equal to K Prime but it has the property
that it's very big namely equal to R
we're imagining R getting very very
large now when uh when K is equal to K
Prime so we've stretched it out to make
the inner
product be a Delta function instead of a
chronica
Delta once we do that we can then
rewrite we can write
the original equation which I haven't
written down but I'll write it down now
that the inner product between two igen
vectors instead of being equal to a
chronica
Delta becomes a Delta function Delta of
K minus K Prime so here was the
step where we stretched out the vector
and made a Delta function out of a
chronica Delta we multiplied each wave
function by the square root of r
notice that the wave functions still
have the square root of 2 pi in
them all right that is where Theon
that's where the chronica Delta became
equal to the Delta
function once we do that we can freely
pass to a notation where sums are
replaced by integrals where chronica
Deltas are replaced by Delta
functions and uh and just comfortably go
ahead
more or less blindly using Delta
functions now I'm not going to say
anything more about it than that right
now
yeah
no not
anymore it's R now but we had let's go
back what we had is if I put r down
here then it was equal to 1 if K is
equal to K
Prime I simply multiplied it through by
the square root of R and another square
root of R and got R
here in other words an inner product was
which was one now becomes an inner
product which is very large if K is not
equal to K Prime that it happens to be a
Delta function a legitimate Delta
function is something that you can prove
but I simply wanted to show you where
the at what stage at what point the
stretching of the vector took place the
stretching by the factor of square root
of
R okay that's
one um important
observation now what I want to do is
show you the connection between momentum
States and position states the momentum
basis and the position BAS
but before I do I want to come to a very
very simple theorem which we've already
studied but get around a little more
right first of
all we've discussed the inner product of
two vectors A B and the inner product of
two vectors is a
number there's another concept which is
the outer product of two vectors the
outer product of two vectors and it's
written this way
B
A this is the inner product of the K
Vector B with the bra Vector a this is
the outer product of the K Vector B with
the bra Vector a what the hell does this
mean this is no longer a number this
object is an operator it's a linear
operator and the way that it works is if
you take this object think of it as a
think of it now as an object in its own
right
just in order to indicate that it's an
object in its own right let's put a a
Red Bracket around
it what you do with this object is you
multiply it by vectors in other words
you act on it with this being thought of
as an operator let's operate on the
vector c what does this
mean right it means just about what the
notation might lead you to believe it
means it means the inner product of a
with
C the a which is adjacent to the C over
here just write down the inner product
of a with C that's a number that is a
number times the vector
B so the result is a
vector this is an operation on vectors
which give vectors times numbers vectors
times numbers are are
vectors the outer product of B with a is
legitimately a linear operator Co it's a
diad it's called a diad and that's what
it
is okay that's uh that's one observation
important observation now another
observation is the following if I have a
basis of
vectors I can expand any Vector in it I
can write that this is a
sum of coefficient v subn no I'm sorry I
did not mean to write this I want to
write v as a vector is a sum of a set of
coefficients times the nth basis
Vector that's what a basis is good for
it's good for writing any Vector as a
sum of the basis vectors what are these
coefficients V subn the coefficients V
subn are equal to the inner products
of
V with the basis Vector
n the coefficients themselves are
nothing but the inner product of the
vector that you're expanding with the
basis vectors themselves this is easy to
prove I think I actually proved it in
class at one point so you can rewrite
this as the
sum of of now let's do it right let's
write let's put first n that's this n
over here and then let's put V suben
which is n *
V you can read this in two ways both of
them are correct the sum is of course
sum Over N all basis vectors two ways
that you can read this you can say first
of all that this is just a sum of
vectors with coefficients the
coefficients being these vs subn but the
other way that you can read it which is
also
correct is to say that we have a set
of vector a sorry a set of
operators these kind of outer product
operators one for each basis
Vector you add what happens when you add
operators you get
operators so you can read this another
way you can read this as saying that
there's a certain
operator let's write it
out a certain
operator I'm going to call it
I and it's equal to the sum of N of the
diads in
N that's what appears here and it has
the property that if you multiply it by
any vector
v you get
v i *
V is equal to
V this operator which is composed out of
the basis of diads is nothing but the
identity operator the identity operator
means the operator which when it hits
any Vector gives back the same
Vector call it the unit operator you can
call it just plain one you can call it I
you can call it a number of different
things but whatever it is it's something
that when you see it it just gives back
the same Vector to begin
with that's a useful
formula let's write it out over here
that the identity operator the thing
which does nothing when it hits a vector
just gives back the same Vector is the
sum over a
basis
of basis Vector of
diads and example of this would be to
take
momentum igen
vectors but if the momenta form a
Continuum if we go to this limit where
the circle is very very big and when we
replace sums by sorry sums by integrals
and chronica Deltas by Delta functions
this becomes I is equal to the integral
over k
of K with
k at some point I'm almost certain I'm
going to lapse into calling
KP and call it the
momentum that's just setting H bar equal
to one so if I do that either yell out
or just swallow it and say he set H bar
equal to one
again yeah um on that formula I equals
the sum to the N would it be right to
say that you could say that would be
instead of calling it n is the sub call
I and N I N I basically I'm kind of
confused by that notation because you
got two l in there yeah
the well this sum is just say sum over
them that's just the summation index
it's just all all the vectors in that
space yes you sum over all the basis
vectors all the basis vectors yeah right
now there may be many bases many
possible
bases many possible bases a basis is
just a set of orthonormal vectors there
may be more than one for example just an
ordinary two-dimensional
space a real two-dimensional space
that's a basis that's a
basis that's a
basis those those
vectors it's the same for any one of
them it's common with an uncountable
basis to just use a letter like Alpha
both as the index and the way you're
using n there for an uncountable basis
yeah just write Alpha the sum over Alpha
even though you can't really sum over it
but it's common to do so but in practice
what it means if the uh if the basis
vectors are labeled by a continuous
variable is it means
integral all right it means integral so
in practice uh to make it
concrete one would write one would
replace the S by an integral and
remember wherever there are inner
products between basis vectors they're
not chronical Deltas they're Delta
functions all right they're Delta
functions all right that's a useful this
is a useful
fact and it is in fact at the at the
heart of fia's theorem about Foria
transforms so let's discuss fia's
theorem and its relationship with
quantum mechanics State vectors
describing particles with definite
positions State vectors describing
particles with definite
momenta and their various wave
functions let's see
um I have too many things in front of me
here ah here it
is
okay
definition if s is a state of a particle
on a line then the and X is an igen
function of position with igen value
given by the label here then the wave
function is by
definition the inner product of the
state
Vector with the igen vector of position
this is called s of
X according to the postulates of quantum
mechanics the product of this with its
complex conjugate s star I is the
probability to find the particle at X or
the probability density to be
precise
okay now let's apply this in particular
to a wave function of definite
momentum let's call
it P ah if I call it P I'm going to have
to put an H bar in let's call it
K this is a definite State Vector
describing a particle with momentum K
and I'm interested in it's in a product
with a particle of position X it's the
wave function of the particle with
momentum K it's the wave function of
that state all right what is
that that is just e to the I
KX over the < TK of 2
pi I've left out the r in here because
I'm going to use Delta functions instead
of chronical Deltas right all I've done
here is to use the wave function that
we've written down up
here thrown away the square root of R in
the
denominator and written that that wave
function s of X is just e to the I KX so
what I've discovered is that the inner
product of a momentum wave function a
momentum state with a position state has
this nice symmetric form notice it's
sort of symmetric between K and x e to
the I KX over the < TK of 2
pi that's one
observation now let's take a more
General State
s and I'm interested in what's the
probability that it has different
momentum here is the probability
amplitude for it to have different
positions
I multiply it by its complex conjugate
to find the probability now I want to
know what's the probability for finding
different momenta if I were to if I were
to measure the momentum instead of the
position well that's related or is equal
to the square of this
quantity k of course being related to
the momentum by a factor of H bar which
I will ignore the inner product of s
with K quantity squared multiply this by
its conjugate call this here let's call
it s twiddle of
K it's the thing that you square to find
the probability for different momenta I
put the twiddle up here to indicate that
it's not just s of X it's a wave
function that depends on momentum not on
position its square is the probability
that the particle has different momenta
if I have if I were to measure the
momentum instead of the position
okay let's uh calculate
that let's calculate that by
using our trick where is our trick our
trick is over
here this is the trick we'll
use what we're allowed to
do is we're allowed to substitute or not
the substitute but insert into any
expression
see which one do I want to put in there
uh excuse me one
minute
yeah
x x
s integral
DX what I've done here this is not quite
what I've used what I've used is I is
also equal to the integral
DX of XX
both of these are bases the K basis and
the X basis the momentum basis and the
position basis the position vectors are
all Au the normal or at least they're
normalized with a a Delta function just
like these K vectors
here and so what I've done in here is to
insert unity in the form of the sum of
diads summing over a
basis okay well what is this object over
here this is of
X what is this object this is e to the I
KX let's see it's actually complex
conjugate of this notice over here I
have K on the right and X on the left
here I have K on the left X on the right
what's the relation between this and
this complex conjugate complex conjugate
so I actually have to put e to the minus
I KX all divided by theare < TK of 2 pi
1 /un of 2
pi integral e to the IX s of X
DX that's equal to what that's equal to
side twidle of
K what's the bottom line the bottom line
is if I want to know the probability for
a given
momentum I take the wave function as a
function of position I multiply it by E
to Theus I KX and I
integrate that gives me a function fun
of K and that function of K is the thing
that you square to find the probability
for different
momentum
okay
so that's the mathematical logic
connecting position and momenta this
operation has a name taking s of X and
multiplying it by E to Theus I KX and
integrating DX is called the Foria
transform
so this is the fora transform the
momentum space wave function s ttle of
K is the Foria transform of the position
space wave
function
okay you can go in the other direction
you can do exactly the same thing to
relate the position space wave function
to the momentum space wave function you
go through exactly the same
operation uh or almost exactly the same
operation let's just uh let's see if we
can do
it let's see what we write is that s of
X
I'm taking this pattern that we have
here but interchanging X and K so s of x
is by definition X x * s that's its
definition and now to calculate it I'll
insert a complete set of momentum States
x
k
s integral
Decay again I have now done exactly the
same thing except I've expressed the
identity operator I as an integral over
k
well what's this this is nothing but
side twiddle of
K this is side twiddle of
K and what is this where is it here it
is right over here it's e to the I
KX integral DK
square otk of 2 pi
right that's s of
X so look we have a reciprocal
relationship between s of K and S of X
on the one hand s twidle of K is gotten
by integrating
overx of s of X with e to minus I KX on
the other hand s of X is gotten by
written by integrating over k of s
twiddle of K let's put the two formulas
down next to each other and compare
them
here side twidle of
K is equal to the integral of e Theus I
KX over < TK 2 piun * I of x if somebody
tells you the position space wave
function you can immediately read all
the momentum space wave function okay
from this formula on the other hand if
somebody tells you the momentum space
wave function you can read off the
position space wave function e to plus I
KX over the < TK of 2 pi s twiddle of
K the only asymmetry here is that one of
them has an e to the minus I KX and the
other has an e to the plus I
KX so this little formula here this type
of formula here is rather
powerful and it encapsulates among other
things the reciprocal relationship of
Foria
transforms that have negative values too
can what have negative values
absolutely absolutely momentum can be
negative just means the particle's going
in the negative Direction
is there a physical interpretation of
that syry between well is there is there
a physical
interpretation
um was not obvious from classical
mechanics that there should be any
reciprocal relationship between momentum
and position at least not until you get
to the Pome bracket formulas where you
begin to see that they are symmetrically
related to each other
this is all very very closely related uh
to to that story of Pome brackets but uh
we're not there yet but this is another
example of the reciprocal relationship
of
momenta and
position okay
good
um here's something you can sort of
guess in other words there are two
representations of the same thing the
representation we have a state
s we can represent that state s in terms
of a wave function s of X whose square
is the probability when I use the word
square I mean times it's complex
conjugate whose square is the
probability for different positions okay
but we can also use a side twiddle of K
which has has the same information how
do I know it has the same information
because you can go back and forth
between
them one simple Vector is described in
two distinct ways one in terms of a wave
function of position and the other in
terms of a wave function of
momentum now let me remind you now how
does the position operator act on S of X
what does it
do multiplies by X this is an operator
now it's not just coordinate X it
multiplies by X and the S of
X okay how about the momentum operator
K thought of as an operator what does it
do to S of
x minus i d by
DX of s of
X now this reciprocal relationship which
I'm not going to prove but it's more or
less clear from the Symmetry pattern
pattern between X and momentum here is
first of
all how do you think the momentum
operator acts on S twiddle of
K well side twiddle of what does it
do multiplies by
k k * s twidle of
K so if we happen to have had the wave
function in the momentum basis called
the momentum
representation if we had the state
Vector expressed in the momentum
representation and we want it to know
how K acts it's easy we multiply by K
how about X how does X act when it acts
on the wave function side twidle of
K what would you
guess plus or
minus
plus plus it's this um funny
asymmetry between plus and minus in the
Foria transform formula it is
plus I D twiddle by
DK all right these are first of all
formulas about Foria transforms first of
all among other
things but there are also formulas about
quantum mechanics these formulas of
course were well known before quantum
mechanics was ever invented by people
who did Foria analysis so they were just
reinvented by quantum mechanics uh for
the purpose of studying particles on a
line for
example
um for the yeah yes so so you can't
represent the state Vector with both of
them it can only be one or the other yes
that's right uh the question
was you you don't represent the the
state either one or the other let's say
either one or the
other you represent the state Vector as
a s of X or a side ttle of K and most
certainly not a function of K and
X
right or you could say it the other way
the Heisenberg uncertainty relation is
uh the fact that the function of X is
that the well this reciprocal
relationship no Vector is both a igen
vector of K and an igen Vector of X all
right so there is no state which has a
definite position and a definite
momentum and in fact it's as bad as it
could be a state of definite momentum
has a completely uncertain position and
by Symmetry by now you can see there's a
symmetry between the two problems so if
a state of definite momentum is smeared
all over the place in position then a
state of definite position has a
completely uncertain
momentum that's the character of the
position versus or the position momentum
correspondence if you
like um Can Can you remind me what the
physical interpretation of conservation
of facebase volume would be other than
just a state restate I can remind you
the conservation of phase based volume
will become the
unitarity of
operator of the time development
operator well just within classical
mechanics I mean like I guess in
classical mechanics the conservation of
the face Space volume is the
conservation of the space face space
volum it doesn't have an interpretation
physically other than just a consequence
of when you do a transformation you get
well you can kind of think of it as the
um as a class classical version of the
statement that um distinctions between
states are
maintained with
time that the phase bace volume doesn't
shrink for example if you start with a
phase Bas volume which looks like this
in Phase space which has many many
points in it it will not evolve to a
single point for example all right if it
did evolved from a single point that
would mean that there was no way to uh
to figure out uh where you came from so
the conservation of phase Space volume
is roughly speaking the statement that
distinctions between different states
are maintained and uh there's a there's
a more quantitative version of it which
is just conservation of phas Space
volume in quantum mechanics it becomes
the unitarity of the uh which we haven't
gotten to
yet uh we may or may not get to it
tonight what unar unitarity
means but unitary is the um quantum
mechanical analog
of what do you call those
transformations in classical mechanics
canonical great which preserve phase
based
[Music]
volume
okay
Sor
here this
one well I just guessed it from
yeah oh that was the defin that was the
original starting point for what
momentum is momentum was the object
represented by the linear operator minus
i d by DX remember we proved that minus
i d by DX was
heran right minus i d by DX = K hat * I
ofx that's the
statement that uh well
thought of as a uh as an operator
equation it's the definition of k hat if
we actually put a definite K here and
said that this was S Sub k s sub K this
would be the igen value equation that
says that the momentum operator acting
on S of K gives us K times uh gives us
the igen value times s but let's just
leave it this way for the moment all
right so I went let's
yeah I may have just confused you and I
didn't mean
to
uh I just guessed this one from this one
but I also know that it's true and it's
easy to work out quite easy to work out
from all the
definitions yes sir uh when we did that
I shouldn't
remember you putting some weasel words
in there some some which weasel words
weasel words weasel
that may or may not have anything to do
with what
we what we think
of no the point is thus far we haven't
established a clear connection between
what we Quantum mechanically calling
momentum and what we classically called
momentum okay let me tell you right now
what that what that connection Is Right
without deriving it let me tell you what
it is
there
are wave
functions for a problem involving a
particle moving in a potential well or
something like that there are wave
functions which hold themselves together
pretty well as long as the potential is
smooth and not too crazy then the motion
of a wave packet what is a wave packet
I'll tell you what a wave packet means
it first of all means that the wave
function s of
X is is
concentrated in some region with a nice
smooth shape perhaps shape that looks
like a bell curve but it doesn't have to
be exactly a bell curve so s of X looks
like this but it also says that the
momentum space wave function is also
that's s of X but here I'm just writing
the magnitude of it I haven't tried to
express the phase of it just the
magnitude of it uh it is of course a
complex thing and I have tried to
indicate how the complex uh part of it
varies across here the magnitude of it
varies like this right it's also
implicit in the notion of a nice wave
packet that s of K Cann that be
seen s of k s twiddle of K is also a
nice concentrated wave function of some
sort you mean those to be gum I gum
would be an example but it doesn't have
to be literally A gaussian a gaussian is
a is a good example but it does not have
to be literally a gaussian right just a
wave function which is concentrated at
some position and concentrated at some K
but not infinitely narrow in X because
if it's infinitely narrow in X it will
be spread all over the place in K and
vice versa all right now if it is
concentrated in
K that means it looks more or less like
a plain wave like an e to the I KX right
right so that must mean that it looks
like this or that the real and imaginary
part of it looks something like that it
oscillates the real and imaginary part
of it oscillate almost as though it were
a momentum wave function but with an
envelope with an envelope that's fairly
concentrated in
X wave functions which look like this
for example you just take e to the I KX
X and multiply it by some function of X
which looks like
that this will be something which is
concentrated in X by virtue of this
Factor but it will also oscillate pretty
much like a plane wave inside that
lump those are wave functions that
describe particles not with very precise
momentum in position but with fairly
precise momentum in
position somewhat precise momentum not
in violation of the uncertainty
principle but more or less um saturating
the uncertainty principle meaning to say
as certain as possible in both position
and momentum now those wave functions
will move they will propagate the
Schrodinger equation which is the
equation which tells you how these
change with time will have these wave
packets moving and they will move more
or less or similar to the motion of a CL
classical particle that's the theorem
that will prove the theorem that will
prove when we finally get to
it is that the center of the wave packet
in position moves very much like the
position of a classical particle in fact
uh as long as the wave function
maintains its shape like this it moves
along like a classical particle and with
time first of all the position will
change with time but also the moment
will change with time that means that uh
for example if the momentum increases
that might mean that the wave packet
gets more and more
oscillating or less and less oscillating
both the momentum and the position will
change the wave packet if it's a nice
problem will maintain its integrity and
move with both a position moving in
space and a k moving in uh in momentum
space the theorem that will eventually
prove is that the centers of these wave
packets move like classical
particles and the center of their
momentum distribution move with the same
equation of motion that the classical
momentum uh evolves with that's the
bridge to classical physics the motion
of wave packets but we're not there yet
so for now we just call these things
position and
momentum and
uh accept on faith that the some
connection between classical momentum
classical position and quantum
mechanical momentum and
position
okay let's uh take a five minute
break a and you say the is a number if
are complex vectors be a complex number
correct where are we up here yeah so are
complex vectors the in product to be a
complex number in general yes so I'm I'm
trying to get my head around what is the
outer product of
comple a non Herm Mission operator in
general now we haven't discussed yes we
have disc once you multiplied it over
there you got
AC it's a which yeah yeah but you can
ask what's the connection
operator operat time k equals K yes but
the question is in what sense is this
complex
okay in what sense is this complex
well it's complex in the sense that it's
not equal to a *
B these are kind of complex conjugates
of each other but strictly speaking the
correct term which I haven't introduced
yet is their hermiss conjugates of each
other we've we've discussed what a
hermiss operator is uh but we have not
discussed what the Herm Mission
conjugate of an operator is and we will
eventually but if you happen to know
what it means this oper operator and
this operator are hermiss conjugates of
each other which is the operator version
of complex
conjugate any other question before we
take a
break okay the thing that we have seen
rather
clearly is the notion of
incompatible
observables incompatible operators that
don't have the same igen functions and
therefore cannot be definite in the same
state we're starting to get some idea
about how the logic of quantum mechanics
works and that it works quite
differently than the logic of classical
mechanics in classical mechanics you
would simply specify a position and a
momentum in quantum mechanics you can
specify a position or a
momentum or you can specify a more
complicated object a wave function s of
X which contains probability
information or you can specify the same
state Vector in terms of a momentum
space wave function which has
information in it about the momentum but
not both but not both not both at the
same time it's one or the
other I like to say that uh that quantum
mechanics often replaces the word and by
the word
or classical physics you might say that
a particle has a position and a momentum
in quantum mechan mechanics you would
say a particle has a position or a
momentum you work in one representation
or the
other and at no point do you ever assign
a notion of probability to more than one
variable if those variables are
incompatible we'll come through examples
of compatible variables but uh the
particle on the line is not a good
example for
that now I want to come to a system
which is in many ways much much
simpler it's a system which has only two
orthogonal
states now the last time I taught this
course I did this exercise by using the
spin of an
electron the spin of an
electron is like a heads or tails uh
coin which if you measure it along some
axis is either up or down and it's never
in between on the other hand you can
measure it along any axis so it gets a
little complicated this time I want to
do a different system which also has two
orthogonal states you can think of it as
a spin of a photon if you like or better
yet the polarization of a photon light
is polarized or light can be polarized
light is made of photons first of all so
think of light as particles now and
we're interested in the quantum
mechanics of those
particles but don't completely forget
the fact that there's also a wave theory
of light okay they've got to be made
compatible somehow let's just go to the
wave theory of light for a minute
there's a notion of the polarization of
light light is an electromagnetic wave
of course and a
typical wave describing a light wave
moving down this uh axis let's say with
a certain wavelength would
be a wave consisting of the electric
field
and in this case the electric field
oscillates in the vertical plane
here positive to negative and so forth
but it also has a magnetic field and the
magnetic field is always perpendicular
to the electric field and so an ordinary
electromagnetic wave let's see let's
let's try to draw
it the magnet this would be the electric
field and there would be the magnetic
field in
the let's see if we can draw it
electric field oscillates in the
vertical
plane and magnetic field oscillates in
the horizontal
plane like
that of course you can rotate it out ofe
they're not out of phase they're in
Phase I just no the the reason this is
lagging behind here is cu I projected it
onto the x- axis is is that drawing
clear
no
h sorry too many people are talking I
can't
hear that's what I'm afraid yeah yeah
okay the picture is clear my question
was should they be out of phase no no
okay no no no no good
no now this is a plain polarized
electric uh uh plain polarized light
wave meaning that the electric field
oscillates in a plane right oscillates
in a plane if this is called the
z-axis and the other two axes are X and
Y and supposing I look at that wave
looking down along the axis we have an X
and A Y AIS and in this case the
electric field is along one of the
directions that electric field and and
the magnetic field perpendicular to it
the definition of the Polar polarization
of a light wave is the direction of the
electric field however we don't
distinguish whether the electric field
is up from whether it's down in other
words we just say for example it's
polarized in the y direction it's an
oscillation up and down in the y
direction but just think of it as a wave
polarized along the Y
AIS or the wave can be polarized ized
along the x
axis or it can be polarized along any
axis the definition of the polarization
is the plane or the direction of the
electric field oscillations that's
arbitrary you could have defined it to
be the magnetic field
oscillations but uh that's how it's
defined now if you take a long
wavelength electromagnetic field
radio waves or
microwaves radio waves let's say and you
run them past a grid a grid consisting
of wires in the vertical axis
here the wave will come out on the other
side polarized it will come out
polarized along a particular axis let's
see does it get polarized along the axis
of the wires or does it get polarized
along the direction perpendicular to the
wires do you
know perpendicular to the
wires perpendicular to the
wires out the wires short out the E
field exactly the wires short out the E
field in the vertical Direction but they
allow the E field in the horizontal
direction to go
through right um there's no current
flowing in the horizontal Direction all
right here's the way to say it okay
here's the way to say it supposing you
just took a
square of conducting material and you
shine light on it what happens to it it
reflects doesn't go through it at all
okay now supposing we take this grid of
wires oh oh how does it reflect what
causes it to reflect what causes it to
reflect is currents that are generated
in the uh piece of metal here for
example an electric field comes in here
starts charges moving the charg is
moving make a reflected wave and the
wave reflects off because it starts uh
because the original wave starts some
current oscillating in the uh in the um
metallic
conductor now here the only direction
that the electric uh field can drive
current is in the vertical Direction
it's not possible to drive current in
the horizontal Direction because there
are no wires in the horizontal Direction
the result is that a vertically
polarized electric field a wave coming
in with vertically polarized electric
field will start a current going and
will get
reflected a wave with its electric field
in this
direction it just behaves exactly as if
there was no grid there it cannot start
any currents going and so it just goes
right through so the field that goes
through to the other side is
perpendicular to the uh direction of the
grid a grid like this is a polarizer at
a microscopic level
roughly speaking a
polarizer is just a grid of lines like
this which transmits through it One
Direction of polarization and either
reflects or absorbs the other direction
sometimes it just absorbs the other
direction sometimes it transmits it
through so that's what a polarizer is
whatever wave falls on it only the
component along the direction of the
axis of the polarizer gets trans
ited okay the direction of the polarizer
happens to be perpendicular to the
direction of the current flow but
nevertheless we speak about the axis of
the
polarizer as the direction of
transmission of the electromagnetic wave
now electromagnetic waves are made out
of
photons
okay if we take a
polarizer let's draw the polarizer this
way this means that it transmits
vertical polarization and we send just a
single Photon through there the single
Photon may or may not pass through if it
happens to be a photon which is
associated with
a electromagnetic wave with vertical
polarization it will pass right through
come out the other side and what's more
it'll come out the other side with the
same polarization that it's started with
on the other hand if it's a photon which
happens to have been associated with a
horizontal
polarization then it won't go through it
may get absorbed or it may get reflected
but in that case nothing comes
out does the reflected Photon polariz
the reflected Photon may be polarized
yes it'll be polarized but I want to
ignore the reflected polar photon
Let's uh it's not hard to imagine a
polarizer which actually absorbs the
other polarization I want to just ignore
the one which is reflected or just let
it be uh just dropped from the picture
if it goes through I count it as a
photon which is successfully passed
through the
polarizer if it gets bounced back it's
for my purpose is
lost now this is a device for for
preparing the particular state of
polarization which we can call vertical
polarization there are two states of
possible polarization now you're going
to ask me what about polarizations at
different angles we'll get to it in a
moment but any given Photon no matter
what the direction of polarization of
the light wave that carried it in other
words no matter how that photon is
prepared it will either get transmitted
or
reflected right either one or the other
even if even if that Photon were
polarized even if the original electric
wave were polarized along some other
axis for example supposing the electric
field of the classical wave describing
uh that's Photon happened to look like
this we let through Photon by Photon one
Photon at a time and we ask what happens
to a
photon you might think that a fraction
of the photon goes through and a
fraction of the photon gets reflected a
fraction of the energy of the photon
goes through and a fraction of the
energy of the photon gets reflected but
no photons are indivisible you can't
break them up like that what happens is
the photon either goes through or it's
reflected it may have a probability for
going through and getting
reflected but it will do one or the
other discrete Choice nothing in between
so there are only two possibilities
the photon makes it through in which
case it's called vertically polarized
when it gets out here or it doesn't get
through in which case it must have been
horizontally
polarized now next fact there's a kind
of
consistency if you manufacture a
vertically polarized Photon this way by
sending it through the vertical
polarizer and it happens to come out
then it is definitely vertically
polarized you can send it through
another vertical polar rizer and it will
with probability one go
through okay so you can think then of
the polarizer as both
a a measuring apparatus and a preparer
of States It prepares States in this
case this polarizer prepared a vertical
polarization but you can also use it to
detect what the polarization is for
example having made it vertical here
if I send it to the next
polarizer if the next polarizer is
vertical it will definitely get through
confirming the fact that it was
vertically polarized if on the other
hand I happened to prepare the photon
with a horizontal polarization just by
rotating the polarizer so that it comes
out this
way then it just gets blocked by this
polarizer so this polarizer can be
thought of as an Apper radus which is
measuring the direction of polarization
of the
photon if it makes it through this
polarizer then it has detected a
vertical polarized Photon if it doesn't
make it through here it has detected a
horizontally polarized Photon okay we
can prepare photons by sending them
through polarizers and we can detect
their polarization by checking what
happens at the next
polarizer so the same apparatus can be
thought of as an apparatus for preparing
a state and measuring a property of the
system as I said if we restrict
ourselves to horizontal to uh to an
apparatus here which measures vertical
which measures polarization what's this
doing this is measuring polarization in
the XY plane it's either vertical or
it's horizontal and this apparatus tells
us whether it's vertical or
horizontal let's start doing some
quantum mechanics let's try to make
quantum mechanics out of
this in other words let's
try using the
formalism that we've concocted to
describe the uh polarization of the
photon we're not going to worry about
the position of the photon we're going
to take the polarization itself as a
system uh and and not worry that that
much about where the photon is where the
photon is all right there are two
orthogonal states of
polarization the two orthogonal states
of polarization we could label first of
all with a K
vector and we could label them this way
this represents polarization along the x
axis we could also just call
it polarization along the x
axis and we could if we like associate
with it a column Vector the column
Vector could be taken to be 1
Z this represents
a this represents the vector polarized
along the x axis represented by a column
Vector with a one here and a zero here
the one indicates that it has
probability amplitude one for being
along the X AIS and zero probability for
being polarized along the other axis
these are three different notations I
could use to describe the same thing
then I have of course the other
possibility that the photon is polarized
in the other direction we could call
that a photon polarized along the Y
AIS or we could call it the column
Vector
01 X and Y are distinguishable distinct
measurably different states of being of
the photon
they are completely distinct if I create
a photon like this and I send it through
the next polarizer if the polarization
is horizontal it will definitely go
through if I create a photon like this
it will definitely not go through so
these are two completely distinguishable
a single experiment can tell you which
of these two states a photon is in and
therefore these must be orthogonal
vectors X and Y Must correspond to
orthogonal States
that of course is consistent with this
notation here remember how we calculate
the inner product between the two
vectors we multiply the first component
times the complex conjugate of the first
component of the other one and so forth
these are two orthogonal vectors so we
can regard these as basis vectors in a
two-dimensional space the two Dimensions
corresponding to the two mutually
exclusive directions of polarization
so this is equal to zero they're
orthogonal on the other hand we can also
choose the vectors describing the two
configurations to be
normalized we can choose
them to be of unit
length in other words we just invent or
concoct a vector space a two-dimensional
Vector space with mutually perpendicular
directions X and Y and unit vectors
along those directions to describe the
two
possibilities this is what quantum
mechanics would tell us to do and these
are then a basis vectors these are then
a pair of basis vectors in a
two-dimensional Vector space this is a
very simple system much simpler than the
particle on a line that's of course
because we're ignoring the motion of the
photon we're just dealing with the
polarization of it just two
possibilities
yeah um is this this thing to do with
observables um before we talked about
observ yeah we haven't yeah we're just
about to do that now okay so the
question is is you said that this these
states are represent polarization one
way or another is that an observable you
can certainly observe it the question
was is that is the polarization and
observable you can observe it you can
send the photon
through a vertical polarizer and it will
either go through or not go through and
that for that will select out for you
whether the photon was vertically
polarized or horizontally polarized so
yes it is an
observable okay we talk about States not
being observable no no the states are
not
observables the things you observe are
the polarization whether whether it is
or isn't horizontal the states represent
the possible configurations of the
photon
the observable is the polariz now we're
going to talk about the the the the uh
the observable that corresponds to the
polarization let's
call let's define an observable
quantity by the following rule that if
the photon is horizontally polarized
Let's uh let's yeah we're going to write
capital this funny P here represents
polarization and it's going to represent
an operator it's our operator which will
represent the polarization of the
photon and it has the property by
definition that if the polarization is
horizontal then p is equal to + one and
if the polarization is vertical it's
equal to minus1 that's a definition now
I will simply assign the number + one to
horizontal polarization and and minus
one to Vertical polarization that's the
thing which becomes the observable it's
either plus one or minus one it has a
numerical value if the photon goes
through the polarizer I assign plus one
if it doesn't go through the polarizer
depending on on the direction of
polarization but we'll Define now a
polarization this is the polarization
operator uh for
polarization in the XY
plane I'm going to put a symbol there
which is intended to show the XY axis
this is the polarization in the XY plane
right and it's equal to plus one for
horizontal
polarization minus one for vertical
polarization that's a definition just in
if we have a bunch of photons going
through and we see one go through let's
say the polar let's assume the polarizer
is oriented along the horizontal
Direction polarizer along the horizontal
direction we send a bunch of pH photons
through if a particular Photon gets
through we put it on Notebook plus if a
photon gets absorbed or reflected we put
in our notebook
minus that way we Define a numerical
quantity which we can call the
polarization but it's the polarization
in the XY plane that's polarization in
the XY plane and here's the way we
Define it as an
operator it
operates when it operates on a polar
ation along the x
axis what does it
give + 1 *
X in other words x is an igen Vector of
this polarization operator with I value
+
one what about polarization along the Y
AIS same operator acting on a different
Vector y
y has I value minus one so this is equal
to minus
y that completely specifies the operator
p with this subscript XY polarization
you know how it acts on X you know how
it acts on Y in fact you know how it
acts on any linear superposition of X
and Y you can even represent it as a
matrix let's represent it as a matrix
if we represent the vector space as
column vectors we can represent the
polarization as a matrix here's the
Matrix here's the Matrix representation
of it it's very simple it's just the
Matrix 1us one 0 0 let's check
it
the X polarization is represent by
represented by one
zero what does this give 1 * 1 + 0 *
0 1 0 * 1 1 * 0
0 so that says that this polarization
operator acting on the X polarization
gives back the X polarization that's
just this equation and let's try the
other one 1 0 0 1 -
one 0
1 1 * 0 is 0 0 * 1 is 1 a zero
0 0 * 0 is 0 -1 * 1 is
-1 and that's equal to minus the
original Vector
01 so in fact this polarization operator
this operator here or this Matrix
represents as a matrix representation of
exactly this operator when it hits the
expolation vector it gives it back when
it hits the Y polarization vector it
gives minus the same thing so this
object capital
P with a hat on top of it is the
observable X's are the igen vectors
which are states of definite
polarization all right the vectors here
the two basis vectors are states of
definite polarization and the observable
polarization the observable the
mathematical observable is represented
by the oper
P any
questions okay so that's
simple but now you say wait a minute
what happens if I Orient my polarizer in
another Direction nothing's to prevent
me from taking my polarizer and
orienting it for
example along the
45 degre
axis there's a well okay here's a
polarizer this is intended to be a piece
of polarizer but the polarizer is
oriented along the 45° axis again we can
send a photon through it what comes out
the other end will be a PO will be a
photon polarized along the 45°
axis obviously
uh this must be a different state than
either one of
these okay but here's the kind of
question you could
ask Let's uh let's draw it a little more
a little better here we have the photon
the polarizer along the 45 degree axes
like that well it can't be both it can
only be one of them uh oriented
along the diagonal Direction like that
and here's another polarizer here I'm
using the first polarizer to prepare the
photon so the photon goes through comes
out the other side which way is it
polarized well it's polarized the way
the polarizer told it to be
polarized uh along the same direction as
the polarizer over here what happens if
the second polarizer is along the same
axis what happens to the
photon it goes through what happens if
the polarizer is oriented this way
it either bounces back or gets absorbed
but what happens if the polarizer is
polarized along one of the
original directions not
this let's let's take it to be along the
x-axis this is the x-axis what happens
if the second polarizer is along the
xaxis rather than the 45° axis then what
happens is the photon either gets
reflected or absorbed nothing in between
the point is even though somehow this
polarization is halfway between the two
possibilities here the photon has no
choice it has no choices which are
halfway between being reflected and
being transmitted it either gets
reflected or transmitted with a
probability right with some probability
all right the question now is what state
and what would you guess the
probabilities to be if this were at 45°
a half and half it's pretty obvious it's
got to be a half and half all right so a
let's now
take let's see how I represented this I
had some uh notation for this here it
is yeah all right so let's take the
photon which has gone through the 45
degree polarizer the polarizer now is
this direction here the photon goes
through it and it comes out the other
side with some definite state that state
is neither X nor y but has an equal
probability for both of them here's a
guess and it turns out to be the right
guess I mean what's right and what's
wrong is determined by experiment so you
do lots of experiments on photons and
you find out that the pattern that I'm
describing is the correct pattern but
what would you expect it to be anybody
want to make a guess what it would
be it's not X it's not y on the other
hand X and Y are a complete basis
there's nothing that can't be written in
terms of X and
Y X+ y seems a reasonable Pro uh a
reasonable possibility the sum of the
two vectors has equal amplitude in both
directions or equal coefficient in both
directions it's not quite right because
it's not
normalized so we throw one over < TK of
two in front of it
now it's normalized the sums of the
squares of the coefficients add up to
one 1 2^ 2 + 1 over 2K 2^ 2 is 1 this
Vector whatever it is has equal has
equal probability that when we send it
through the next
polarizer which happens to be oriented
along the
xais it has probability 1/2 going
through if we send it through the
polarizer
along the Y
AIS it also has probability a half going
through right so this is a superposition
of the two original states with equal
coefficients that's my guess if you like
that's a guess for the photon which is
polarized halfway in
between we can also write it another way
let's see this is this
is photon polarized along the 45 axis is
this which we can also represent I'm
using an equal sign but I should be
using a sign that says it can be
represented by a column vector and the
column Vector would be 1/ < tk2 1 over <
tk2 now these vectors are not oh this is
okay this is one vector now there's a
second polarization the second
polarization is orthogonal to this and
is in this
direction what happens if I send this
polarization let's
through this polarizer supposing I
create a photon with this polarization
in the minus 45° Direction and I send it
through the polarizer in the plus 45
degree Direction
right so we would expect then that the
state Vector describing polarization
along
the minus 45° axis would be orthogonal
to the state Vector of a photon along
the plus 45 degree
axis so let's see if we can find the
vector which is orthogonal to this
vector
well it's not very hard to find a vector
which is orthogonal to this
Vector it's just X over < TK 2 minus y
over <
tk2 represented by 1 < tk2 minus 1/ <
tk2 let's check that these are
orthogonal first of all they're both
normalized both of them the sums of the
squares of the coefficients add up to
one no question of that are they
orthogonal to each other yes to check
whether they're orthogonal you take this
times the complex conjugate of
this everything's real here so I can
ignore the word complex conjugate this
times this plus this times this all
right that's 12 minus 12 the inner
product between them is zero so they're
normalized they're orthogonal to each
other these two vectors are also a basis
this basis is just just as good and has
just as much rights as the original
basis it's just describing polarizations
in Caddy Corner
directions okay what is the
probability that if I create this
polarization and then send it through
the vertical polarizer the Y
polarization what's the probability that
it goes through well of course the
answer answer is a half but let's do it
by using the rules of quantum
mechanics I want to know the
probability that if I
start with 45 polarization like that 45
degree polarization like that and then I
send it through the vertical polarizer
the Y polarizer this is the Y polarizer
that it goes through to the other side
side in other words what's the
probability that this has y polarization
uh uh that it has y polarization the
answer as always is take the inner
product of the vector describing the
photon with the configuration that
you're testing
for what would that be that would be
Y and then take the square of
that that's the probability
that this cattywampus polarization over
here is polarized along the y direction
the inner product of this with this
squared what is it well it's easy to
figure out uh let's just do it
mechanically this guy over here is X
over < tk2 + y over <
tk2 that's this one and this one over
here is just y
well the inner product of Y with X is
zero the inner product of Y with Y is 1
so the answer is 1 over theare < TK of
two that's the thing before you square
it this is the amplitude the amplitude
gets squared to find the probability so
the probability
is square of
this which is just square of this which
is
1/2 all right now I'm telling you
something which is completely obvious
that the probability is a half but I'm
showing you how the formalism of quantum
mechanics uh carries out that
intuition what about the probability
that it's polarized along the
x-axis you do exactly the same
thing again the only contribution comes
from XX here again it's 1/ < TK of 2^2
again it's 1
12 right how
about the second diagonal polar I'll
call this diagonal the second diagonal
polarization pointing along Theus 45°
axis for that I have to put minus
Here and Now using the second Vector
over here with a minus
sign uh sorry this is y this this is the
probability
that this photon is in the up in the in
the y direction right again now we get
minus 1 / <
tk2 but when we Square minus 1 / < TK
of2 we again get a half I don't need to
go through the last possibility the
probabili for both of these in either
the x or y direction is a half so either
photons prepared this way or this way if
sent through a vert iCal or horizontal
polarizer have a probability of 1/2
going through that's not too surprising
I mean that uh that certainly follows
intuitively but it follows from the
mathematical formulas that we've written
down here's a new observable we've now
concocted a new observable the new
observable is not the polarization in
the XY plane but it's the polarization
in the
45° plane for example we could Define it
to be plus for this polarization and
minus for this
polarization this is a kind of rotation
of the polarization uh
observable we can define a new
observable this new observable we will
say is plus one for this and minus one
for that can we make a operator for
which this is an IG state with IG value
+ one and this an igen state with igen
value minus one here's the polarization
operator for
uh for the XY plane now we want to find
the polarization operator for the 45°
directions let's give that polarization
operator a
name let's call it
this there's a bit of arbitrariness do
we call this having plus one and this
minus one or do we call this one having
plus one and this minus one but let's
fix it for the rotated polarization
operator let's say that this has
polarization + one and this one minus
one okay then we want a polar a operator
which has the
property that it gives +
one times this and the same operator
should give
minus1 on this
polarization this would Define a
observable that's associated with
polarization in the uh in the 45 degree
Direction in other words it would be the
polarization observable for a polarizer
oriented in this
direction can we find such an operator
sure the easiest way is to do it using
matrices let's find the Matrix uh let's
let's see if we can find a matrix which
does that I'm just going to write it
down I'm not going to bother finding it
I'm just going to write it down easy
enough to explore around a little bit
and find
it
this is given by The Matrix The Matrix
which represents it is just 1 1 0
0 off diagonal like this off the
diagonal let's check it let's check that
this
polarization
observable multiplies this Vector to
give back the same vector and multiplies
this one to give minus
it all right let's uh go to another
Blackboard let's see where shall we do
this I guess uh I guess just over
here all right so what this
says is that the
Matrix 0110
that's the uh conjectured form for this
polarization
observable multiplies this Vector but
that's
just 1/ < TK of two 1/ < TK of
two to give let's see what it gives 0 *
this is 0o 1 time this
is 1 over < TK two 1 overun two
check that okay so first of all when it
hits this Vector it gives back the same
one let's see what happens when it hits
the other
Vector 0 1 1 0 the other polarization
looks exactly the same except it has a
minus 1 < tk2 here so we write 1un 2- 1/
of two let's do this one a little more
carefully 0 times this element is 0o 1
time this element
is minus 1 over > two and then go to the
second row 1 * < TK 2 + 0 * this is just
1/ < TK
two notice that this Vector is minus
this
Vector the vector we started with was
1/2 minus
1/2 the vector we wound up with was
exactly the same except with a minus
sign in front of it is minus the
original
Vector so in fact this operator this
Matrix represents the operator that
we're looking for and represents the
observable polarization the polarization
observable for the XY
plane notice that there is no Vector
which is simultaneously an igen Vector
of this polarization observable and this
polarization
observable the igen vectors of the
vertical horizontal XY
polarization are just X and Y here the
igen vectors of the 45° rotated
polarization are the linear combinations
X + Y and xus Y there are no common igen
vectors and this means that these to two
polarizations are incompatible you
cannot measure both of them
simultaneously in other words there is
no polar there is no polarization
experiment which can tell you
simultaneously what the XY polarization
is and what
the rotated
polarization there are experiments which
can tell you the XY polarization there
are experiments which can tell you the
rotated polarization but there's no
experiment which can tell you both
because there are no simultaneous igen
vectors of these two
in other words they're sort of like
position and momentum two incompatible
quantities if you know one of them you
can't know the other if you know the
other you can't know the first so these
are um another example of
incompatibility next time we'll explore
more complicated states of
polarization we haven't discussed what
happens if the polarization is some
along some arbitr
angle I did not intend this to look like
45° if it does I think it doesn't but I
in case it does it was not intended to
be at 45° what happens if it's at
15° and a perpendicular one which is at
90 + 15 would be
105° how do we describe that what are
the igen vectors that describe it and
what is the polarization observable that
describes it the one you can be sure of
is that it will be incompatible with the
other two that I've already
described so there's no compatibility
between the polarization observables in
any two different
directions uh oh that's not quite
true is there anything well if you
rotate by
90° that's trivial that uh just uh that
just changes X into Y and of course
they're uh
it basically just multiplies the
polarization by minus one what was the
what had plus polarization becomes minus
never mind uh as long as we're talking
about distinctly different axes of
polarization then there are no
simultaneous igen vectors as we'll see
and so they're all a mutually
incompatible set of uh polarization
observables that's what makes this
interesting so far notice that
everything we've written down has no
comp complex numbers in
it why is
that yeah that's we're discussing a
subset of the possible kinds of photons
which are plain
polarized if we put complex numbers in
then we're studying circularly polarized
left and right and we'll do that also so
there's more polarization States than
just those which are plain polarized
there are also polarization states which
are circularly polarized and we'll
discuss that uh circularly polarized
light next time
yeah the probability
ofs to be observable y you don't have an
operator for it you
just wait excuse me what what I've been
doing here is the observables for
polarization uh what are you
saying X has an operator X position
I'm missing your
question it seems like
probability probability is not
unobservable probability you cannot
measure for a particle you measure
probability by measuring many many many
particles but in a single experiment you
cannot measure the probability so
probability is not counted as an
observable the polarization is an
observable you send it through a
polarizer it either gets reflected or it
doesn't get reflected a single
experiment and you get a number that
number goes into your list and it's uh
it's it's an observable quantity for
each
experiment well wait let me I I'm so I
don't want to mix up language probably
ility is not
unobservable
it's what's that like end up with a
number
half I didn't mean to say you can't
observe the probability I said a
probability is not an observable that's
a technical that's a technical term
observable it's a thing which you can
measure in a single experiment you
cannot measure the probability in a
single experiment all you'll get is a
plus one or a minus one with no way to
determine what the probability is in a
single experiment so observables are
things that you measure in a single
experiment on the system and you get a
definite answer there's no way to get a
definite answer for a probability
without doing the same experiment over
and over and over again and accumulating
lots of Z of minus ones and plus
ones so by according according to the
official language that we use
probability is not an observable the
polarization is an observable that
doesn't mean we don't uh that we don't
observe the probability but to do so
we'd have to do a lot of repeated
experiments I think I think what he's
trying to say is something like this you
have something in a particular state has
been prepared you
have one Photon uh this phap thingy that
that you use that you're going to
observe and then you have a third thing
which is sort of that's the possible
result that you're considering is and
then you get a probability by squaring
that whoa whoa whoa whoa wait a minute
let's use language correctly you know
the pro the things that you can get wait
minute the things that you can get the
answers you can get are the igen values
the possible answers you can get are the
igen values you don't Square the igen
values to get probabilities I just mean
that you take the state you hit it with
the operator the
observable and you to um form the inner
product of that resulting C with the bra
for the particular result that you're
considering the probability of you take
the vector describing the
system okay you don't hit it with the
observable you just take its inner
product with the igen vectors with two
possible igen vectors of the
observable X or Y
and from these you get
probabilities by
squaring all right so the role of the
observable is to tell you or the
observable operator here is to tell you
what the possible values that you can
get and which states have definite
values when you know which states have
definite values I might have begun I
might have begun with the operators
rather than the states I might have said
this this is an
observable this is an observable here
are its igen vectors and its igen values
are plus one and minus one about is
right there okay MH where you write X
over here on the at the BR here over
here at the brao yeah okay it's really
the complex conjugate of p+ of X using
the I value
equation sorry it's just the it's just a
complex conjugate of the vector X
yeah it's also complex conjugate of the
left side of the equal sign yeah to have
it in in this particular case so in that
particular case you're also able to
write it with the p in the same in
product yeah but you don't want to do
that generally you don't want to do that
generally okay you don't want to do that
generally what you generally want to do
is take the inner product of the vector
with the Igan Vector of
P that's the general rule take the
Vector in question that you prepared
take its overlap or its inner product
with an igen Vector of the observable
and square that to get
probability is observable the say is
that synonymous with heran operator or
is there some situation all observables
are her Mission operators and all
Mission operators are observables
right that the that you you didn't have
to choose numbers one and minus one you
could have chosen right right I could
have chosen one and zero or I could have
chosen right9
absolutely absolutely so there's an
ambiguity in what the Observer writes
down in his notebook but having chosen
his convention to call one polarization
one and the other polarization 7 you
stick with it had he done that the
operator would have been let's see where
is uh capital P then we would have
written this and 70 over here and the
Matrix would have been
17 an interesting case would have been 1
Z no it's it's as interesting or as
expectation the expectation value of
that operator would be the
probability as in fact it would be yes
that's
correct that's correct okay so we can
actually make a correct statement using
all right good good good all all right
so let me let's uh let me give you the
precise statement which you just gave a
special example
of take this Vector okay take this
vector and let's construct out of this
Vector not this observable but another
operator namely the diad made like this
okay you understand what this thing is
this is a special case of the diads that
we spoke about
before okay now take the vector that
we're interested in and
sandwich the
diad this operator incidentally this
operator is represented by one0 just as
you
said okay sandwich the vector
or use the the vector is the bread the
salami is the uh is the diad in between
make a sandwich like this and this of
course is the probability because it's
the inner product of s with the igen
vector of of the observable
squared okay there's another diad we can
make the other diad we could make is
this
one this expression is the prob
probability to find X polarization this
expression is the probability to find y
polarization but neither of these two
diads happens to be
this what is this this happens to
be the difference of the two
diads but uh I didn't you asked the
question so I gave you a fairly complete
answer but uh it uh was not what I had
intended to talk about does that answer
your
question no it answers it but you may
not understand
it no yeah me yeah yeah no I I I a
comment question I know but did you
understand my reaction to your comment
yeah okay good good good okay yeah your
comment happens to be right but it's
only more somewhat accidental yeah no
what your comment is right your comment
is right this you could have defined the
observable this way and then the
expectation value of it would be the
probability
right
right but the but the output would be
one or zero not the probability the
output of the experiment would be one or
zero that's right that's right the
zero so I think to get to his comment it
seems like that the real observable is
the exclusion
that the polarization is not
perpendicular to what it's pass through
as opposed to that
it's is what it's been filtered through
know the only you know is it's not
0 off of what the is supposed to be
passing through say
again you if you if you're polarized on
the on the Y AIS having
you have a 50% chance of being 45°
either way 0% Z probability of being
perpendicular to that polarization so
the observ really is the exclusion of
the perpendicular to the
polarization um there are there is more
than one observable that we're talking
about which one are you talking about
you talking about this
one talking about this one talking about
the X X Y yeah this one yeah
well this observable is the observable
that's associated with a
polarizer that's polarized along the XY
AIS it's the observable that's measured
by sending the photon through a
polarizer that is either along the X
direction or the y
direction okay that's what it is or if
you like to be precise it's the
observable that's
recorded by an an observer who writes
down plus one if it goes through that
polarizer minus one if it doesn't go
through that
polarizer
um I don't know any other way to say it
to be very precise about it the
particular observable is identified with
a particular apparatus for making a
measurement in this case the apparatus
is a polarizer and the polarizer let's
say in the vertical Direction the
observable that's associated with it can
be taken to be that thing over there
because you could Define it differently
as somebody said you didn't have to
define the igen values to be plus one
and minus one I did that for convenience
I could have defined them to be 15 and
42 that would have made very little
difference to the
discussion I chose to Define them plus
one and minus one for for symmetry
reasons but be careful with language the
language is that the observable is
identified with a particular
apparatus and it records or it has to do
with the value of the thing that you
would write down in your notebook after
having let the system interact with the
apparatus and then look at the
apparatus so it's a thing that has to do
with one
experiment uh not a repeated bunch of
experiments and it's the little thing
you record in your notebook event by
event
good everybody
[Music]
happy the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu